

SAQER ALESSA

Saqer_F@hotmail.com | 549555055 Riyadh, Riyadh Region

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Over 10 years IT professional with impressive experience in IT Project Management, IT Governance, Change Management, information technology standards, compliance and controls as well as quality assurance. Handling high-end projects possessing specific proficiency in providing high-tech solutions.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Change and Release management, Service demand and IT Governance.
- IT Project Management & Planning and ATM Operation.
- IT Operation and Network Support Engineer.

WORK HISTORY

IT Change and Release Management and IT

01/2019 - CURRENT

Governance | Saudi Investment Bank - Riyadh, Riyadh Region

Change Management:

- Manage all changes from end to end.
- Enforce our entry and exit criteria
- Ensure that all needed documents are in place and all needed approval are obtained.
- Leading the change management activities within a structured process framework.
- Designing the strategic approach to managing change and support operations that fall within the domain of change management.
- Evaluating the change impact and organizational readiness to limit potential risk.
- Evaluating the risk of change and providing actionable guidelines on reducing the impact.
- Evaluating resistance in adopting the change at the user, process, and technology level.
- Managing the change portfolio, which allows the organization to prepare for and successfully adopt the change.
- Authorize minor change requests and coordinate with the Change Advisory Board for changes presenting higher risk.

Release Management:

- Managing, planning, scheduling and negotiating release activities.
- Managing checklist and deployment plan execution.
- Managing the development of deliverables into production.
- Ensuring that requirements are clear across dependent project streams with a release.
- Ensuring that releases operate as per expectations.
- Managing relationships working on interrelated processes.
- Communicating crucial release plans and changes.
- Coordinating processes between different teams.
- Conduct post-implementation reviews to assess the decisions and performance related to the change request.
- Communicating necessary release details to business teams.

- Measuring and monitoring progress to achieve timely software releases within defined budgetary limits and defined quality standards.
- Conducting release readiness and milestone reviews.
- Managing the deployment of deliverables to the test environment particularly guaranteeing that external dependent item are available the test runtime.

IT Governance:

- Responsibility for governance and audit of information technology procedures.
- Monitor compliance with IT systems.
- Measuring strategic performance and the extent of implementation of strategic objectives.
- Supervising the overall quality raising in all IT processes and procedures.
- Follow up the risk register for information technology.

IT Project Management and Planning Officer | Saudi 12/2016 - 12/2021 Investment Bank - Riyadh, Riyadh Region

- Developing project plans, goals, and budgets; identifying resources needed.
- Developing schedules and methods for measuring results.
- Guiding and performing strategic analysis for the project.
- Controlling time management and organizing and managing all phases of the project to ensure on-time completion.
- Assembling and coordinating project team members; assigning individual responsibilities.
- Preparing requests for proposals and conducting all necessary meetings to facilitate the selection of project services and products.
- Planning and overseeing the preparation and dissemination of project communications.

ATM Operation Supervisor | Ebttikar Technology 07/2014 - 11/2016 Company - Riyadh, Riyadh Region

- Managing ATM Operation Dept. & Staff.
- SLA Improvement.
- Process Improvement.
- Managing ATM Presentations.
- Dashboard Enhancement.
- Managing ATM Projects.
- ATM Data Analyst.
- Running SAMA, Vendors, Sector Performance Reports.
- Fixing System Gaps ((APTRA Vision, Postilion and Gasper)).

IT Operation Engineer and Network Center Support | 05/2012 - 06/2014 Arabic Computer System Company - Riyadh, Riyadh Region

IT Operation Engineer:

- Computer Hardware and Software Issues.
- Providing solutions to the day-to-day problems of the users.
- Analyze and first-level troubleshoot of all issues.
- Understanding Windows booting and troubleshooting booting issues.
- Work on day to day issues related to Production Network, Servers, Applications, or any issues that are brought by the End-user which are related to IT.

Network Operation Center:

- Reacting to network alarms and alerts in order to provide proactive notification of issues.
- Escalate issues in a timely and effective manner to management and to the technical authority.
- Monitor all aspects of Network, Systems, facilities infrastructure and provide outbound communications.
- Monitoring operations of all backbone links and network devices.
- Monitoring core routers and switches.
- Monitoring operations of Bank Website, Retail Internet Banking, Corporate Internet Banking, CRM, etc.
- Worked on applications like Next think, Aptra Vision, Gasper, and Symantec Endpoint Protection Manager.

SKILLS

- Communication Active listening.
- Research Strategic thinking
- Measurement and analysis.
- Collaboration Planning and forecasting
- Risk management Budgeting
- Tracking and monitoring
- Project management methodologies
- Leadership Time management
- Problem solving Adaptability.

SOFTWARE SKILLS

- HTML
- JavaScript
- CSS
- MySQL
- PHP
- Linux

EDUCATION

College of Communications, Riyadh Bachelor Of Computer Engineering

College of Communications, Riyadh Diploma of IT Support Expected in 09/2022

05/2011

CERTIFICATIONS

- Cisco Certified Network Associates (CCNA)
- Cisco Certified Information Technology (IT)
- Adaptive Project leadership Certificate.
- Change Management.
- IT service Management ISO20000.
- Project Management Institute (PMI)
- Risk Management (PMI).
- Six Sigma Black Belt.